Guide to the Lansing V. Hammond Collection of Hugh Thomson
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lansing V. Hammond collection of Hugh Thomson
1879-1958
GEN MSS 69
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7
(12 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
Collection contains materials collected by Lansing V. Hammond documenting the life and career of Hugh Thomson, including correspondence, writings, artwork and other papers. Correspondence includes originals and copies of letters by Thomson, as well as correspondence of M. H. Spielmann, friend and co-author with Walter Jerrold of the Thomson biography entitled Hugh Thomson, His Art, His Letters, His Humor and His Charm, with Thomson's widow Jessie Naismith Miller Thomson, Walter Jerrold and others. Writings include research notes, drafts, proofs and other materials related to Spielmann's biography of Thomson. Artwork contains many original drawings and watercolors by Thomson, some copies and photographs of his works, and drawings by C. E. Brock and H. M. Brock. Other papers include clippings, catalogs of exhibitions, printed material, sales catalogs and other material related to Thomson.
Hammond, Lansing V. (Lansing Van der Heyden), 1906-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lansing V. Hammond, 1942-1966.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials in box 12 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
HUGH THOMSON, 1860-1920
Hugh Thomson was born on 1 June 1860 in Coleraine, Northern Ireland. He was educated in Coleraine, and as a young man worked for Marcus Ward & Co., a Belfast publishing company. While employed there, he was befriended by John Vinycomb, the head of the company's Art Department and a member of the Royal Irish Academy, who served as an early mentor for the artist. Thomson moved to London in 1883, where he met William Comyns Carr, the editor of The English Illustrated Magazine. Thomson submitted his artwork to the magazine, and he soon became a frequent contributor. In 1884 he married Jessie Naismith, a woman from Belfast, with whom he had one son.
While Thomson often contributed illustrations to periodicals such as The English Illustrated Magazine and The Graphic, he was perhaps better known through his illustrations of popular books. He illustrated a series of books called Highways and Byways, many new editions of works by Jane Austen, Charles Dickens and George Eliot, as well as more contemporary works by James Lane Allen and Austin Dobson.
After several years of poor health, Thomson died of heart disease on 7 May 1920 in England.
Scope and Contents
The Lansing V. Hammond Collection of Hugh Thomson consists of material collected by Hammond documenting the life and career of Hugh Thomson. The collection contains correspondence, writings, drawings and other artwork, newspaper clippings and other papers, and has been arranged in four series: Correspondence, Writings, Artwork, and Other Materials.
Series I, Correspondence (1883-1958), contains original letters from Thomson, as well as typescript and holograph transcripts of his letters. These transcripts were most likely made by M. H. Spielmann, a Thomson friend and scholar, in preparation for his biography (co-authored with Walter Jerrold) Hugh Thomson, His Art, His Letters, His Humor and His Charm (1931). Also included are copies and a few originals of letters from Spielmann, letters to Spielmann, and some third-party letters.
Series II, Writings (1892-1935), contains research notes, written reminiscences about Thomson by various people, holograph and typescript drafts, proofs, reviews and other materials related to Spielmann's Thomson biography. Also included are writings by M. H. Amshewitz, Isidore Spielmann, John Vinycomb, and materials related to M. H. Spielmann's entry on Thomson for the Dictionary of National Biography.
Series III, Artwork (1879-1923), contains original ink, pencil and watercolor works by Thomson, primarily created as book and magazine illustrations. Illustrations for works by James Lane Allen, F. J. Harvey Darton, Mary Russell Mitford, and William Makepeace Thackeray are well represented in the collection. Also included in this series are works by C. E. Brock and H. M. Brock.
Series IV, Other Materials (1887-1957), includes newspaper clippings, exhibition catalogs and invitations, printed material, sales catalogs, dust jackets, photographs and other papers.
Artists -- Great Britain; Illustrators -- Great Britain; Illustrators; Drawings (visual works); Watercolors (paintings); Artists; Brock, C. E. (Charles Edmund), 1870-1938; Brock, H. M. (Henry Matthew), 1875-1960; Hammond, Lansing V. (Lansing Van der Heyden), 1906-; Jerrold, Walter, 1865-1929; Spielmann, M. H. (Marion Harry), 1858-1948; Thomson, Hugh, 1860-1920; Thomson, Jessie Naismith Miller
- Correspondence, 1883-1958; Series I; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  - LETTERS FROM HUGH THOMSON
    - Original Letters
      - Darton, Joseph W., 1894 Jun 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Johnson, Mrs., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner & Co., 1892 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Macmillan, Mrs., 1901 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Melville, Lewis, 1909 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Redway, George[?], 1892-96 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Scope and Contents
        Includes: Letter from Frank Hollings to Lansing V. Hammond, 1941
      - Spielmann, M. H., 1892-02, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Includes: 2 New Year's cards with drawings by HT
      - ----, Arthur, 1914-19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Transcripts of Letters
      - Allen, Grace, 1894 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Allen, Hugh, 1899 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Brown, Oliver, 1891-1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Carr, J. Comyns (Joseph Comyns), [n.y.] Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Chuter, A. G., 1917-20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Collins, J. P., 1906-16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Craig, J. A.
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Swain, J., Box 1, folder 30
      - Darton, Mrs., 1916 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Includes: Letter to MHS from F. J. Harvey Darton, 1922
      - Dobson, Alban B., 1901-13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Dobson, Austin, 1885-1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Ernest Brown & Phillips, 1911-13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Includes: Transcript of letter by Jessie Thomson to EB&P
      - Gilbert, Arthur, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Gwynn, Stephen Lucius, [1898?] (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Jerrold, Walter, 1906-17 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
      - Lawrence, C. E. (Charles Edward), 1916 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Layard, George Somes, 1898 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Melville, Lewis, 1908-13 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1887 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Includes: Transcript of letter to MHS from Moore, 1921
      - Robinson, Mr., 1918 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Spielmann, Isidore, Sir, 1917-20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Sutcliffe, George, 1918 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Includes: Letter to MHS from George Sutcliffe, 1921
      - Swain, J., 1884 Feb (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Includes: Letter to J. A. Craig on same page
      - Thomson[?], John, 1890 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Vinycomb, John, 1883-1913 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Empty envelope originally containing letter transcripts, with holograph notes, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - LETTERS FROM M. H. SPIELMANN
    - A. & C. Black Ltd., 1929-32 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1930 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      See also: Barrie, J. M. to M. H. Spielmann, Box 2, folder 59
    - Blackwood, James H., 1931 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Carey, Joseph William, 1931 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Cohen, Mrs. Leonard, 1921-22 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Collins, J. P., 1931 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Dibdin, E. Rimbault (Edward Rimbault), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Dictionary of National Biography, 1925 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dobson, Alban B., 1923 Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Ferguson, Milton J., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Jerrold, Walter, 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Konody, Paul G. (Paul George), 1931 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Low, H. A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Includes: Reproduction of "The Book- sellers Dinner," drawing by HT
    - Macmillan, William E. F., 1931 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Pike, W. T., 1930 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Thomson, Jessie Naismith (Miller), 1922-32 (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
    - Thomson[?], John, 1932 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Whyte, Frederic, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Unidentified, 1921-31 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - LETTERS TO M. H. SPIELMANN
    - A. & C. Black Ltd., 1927-33 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - A. & F. Pears Ltd., 1930 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Allen, Grace, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Allen, William S., 1921 Oct 17 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - The Athenaeum, Pall Mall (London), 1931 Dec 11 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1931 Nov 29 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Includes: Draft of letter from MHS
    - The Bookman
      See: Series IV, Other Materials, The Bookman, Box 8, folder 294
    - Brown, Oliver F., 1921, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Includes: Reproduction of a bookplate by HT
    - Carey, Joseph William, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Cassell and Co. Ltd., 1921[?] (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1921 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Chuter, A. G.
      See: Series II, Writings, Reminiscences, O. Pelly Dick, Box 3, folder 145
    - Coleraine Borough Council (Northern Ireland), 1930 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Collins, J. P., 1921-23, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Croft, Nancy, [n.y.] Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Darton, F. J. Harvey (Frederick Joseph Harvey), 1921-31, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
      See also: Darton, Mrs. from Hugh Thomson, Box 1, folder 15
    - Dawkins, Bertha, 1921 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Dibdin, E. Rimbault (Edward Rimbault), 1926 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Dick, C. H. [Charles Hill?], 1930, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Dick, O. Pelly, 1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Dictionary of National Biography, 1923-25 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Includes: Letters from Margaret Toynbee and J. R. H. (John Reginald Homer) Weaver
    - Dobson, Alban B., 1921-31 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Includes: Copies of two poems by Austin Dobson about HT
    - Dodd, Edith S., 1931 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Dodd, W. H., 1921 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      See also: Series II, Writings, Hugh Thomson..., carbon typescript, Box 5, folder 190
    - Duff, D. G., 1923 Aug 30 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Ernest Brown & Phillips, 1923 Jun 14 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - F. & E. Stoneham, Ltd., 1921 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Ferguson, Milton J., 1932 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Gilbert, Arthur[?], 1921 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Ginn and Company, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Gwynn, Stephen Lucius (fragment), [n.y.] Aug 20 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Hardie, Martin
      See: Victoria and Albert Museum, Box 2, folder 115
    - Henk[?], W. V., 1921-31 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Jerrold, Clare, 1931, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Jerrold, Walter, 1918-29 (Box 2, Folder 85-86)
    - Layard, George Somes, 1922 Oct 2 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Macmillan & Co., 1930, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      Includes: Letters from Frederick Macmillan
    - Macmillan, Frederick, 1931-32 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      See also: Macmillan & Co., Box 2, folder 88
    - Macmillan, George A., 1931 Nov 29 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Macmillan, William, 1931 Jul 2 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Matz, B. W. (Bertram Waldrom), 1922 Apr 7 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Modder, Montagu Frank, 1924 Nov 14 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Moore, Frank Frankfort
      See: Moore, Frank Frankfort from Hugh Thomson, Box 1, folder 26
    - Partridge, Bernard, 1922-23 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Pike, W. T., 1915 Apr 19 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      Includes: Clipping of a biographical statement about John Vinycomb
    - Pitcher, William J. C., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      Includes: Typescript of chapter 9 from MHS's Hugh Thomson, His Art, His Letters, His Humor and His Charm
    - R. & R. Clark (Firm), 1921 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Redway, W. E., 1922 Mar 4 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Royal Institute of Painters in Water Colour (Great Britain), 1921 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Salaman, Malcolm C. (Malcolm Charles), 1921 Sep 14 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Scottish Provident Institution, 1921 Nov 12 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Seeley, Service & Co. Ltd., 1921, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - The Sphere, 1930 Oct 23 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - The Studio, 1921 Sep 20 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Sutcliffe, George
      See: Sutcliffe, George from Hugh Thomson, Box 1, folder 29
    - Thomas, Carmichael, 1931 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Thomson, Jessie Naismith (Miller), 1921-32, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 106-110)
      See also: Series II, Writings, Pages from a looseleaf research notebook, Box 3, folder 139
    - Thomson, John, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Thomson, Mary, 1931 Nov 2 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Thomson, Richard, 1921-31 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Toynbee, Margaret
      See: Dictionary of National Biography to M. H. Spielmann, Box 2, folder 72
    - Verney, Harry, 1922 Jan 9 (Box 2, Folder 114)
      Secretary to Mary, Queen, consort of George V, regarding MHS's proposal to dedicate the biography of HT to the Queen
      Includes: Draft letter by MHS to a lady-in-waiting, 1931
    - Victoria and Albert Museum, 1922 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 115)
      Includes: Letter from Martin Hardie
    - Vincent, Mary A., 1923 Aug 24 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Vinycomb, John, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 117)
      See also: Series II, Writings, Reminiscences, Joseph W. Carey, Box 3, folder 142
      See also: Series II, Writings, Reminiscences, John Vinycomb, Box 3, folder 149
    - Way, George O., [n.y.] Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Weaver, J. R. H. (John Reginald Homer)
    - Whiteing, Richard, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Unidentified, 1922-30, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - THIRD-PARTY LETTERS
    - Brown, Oliver to unidentified (fragment), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Carter, H. R. to A. & C. Black Ltd. (copy fragment), 1931 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Chapman, Dinda[?] to O. Pelly Dick
      See: Series II, Writings, Reminiscenses, Dinda Chapman, Box 3, folder 144
    - Dobson, Austin to Arthur Waugh (printed version of letter), 1910 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Gale, Norman to Mr. Hutchinson, 1893 Jun 6 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Hammond, Lansing V. to Marjorie G. Wynne, 1951-58 (Box 2, Folder 125)
      Christmas cards with reproductions of drawings by HT
    - Hollings, Frank to Lansing V. Hammond
      See: Redway, George from Hugh Thomson, Box 1, folder 6
    - Macmillan & Co. to Mrs. Leonard Cohen, 1922 Mar 20 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Muir, Percy H. to Lansing V. Hammond
      See: Series III, Artwork, "Young Illigits," Box 7, folder 278
    - Shelbourne, Philip, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 127)
      Greeting cards with color reproductions of the drawings "Miss Phoebe's Class" and "Quality Street" by HT
    - Thomson, Jessie Naismith (Miller) to Mrs. Leonard Cohen, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Vinycomb, John to Jessie Naismith (Miller) Thomson, 1921 Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - ----, Janet and Walter to "Cousin Eliza", 1924 Jan 24 (Box 2, Folder 130)
- Writings, 1892-1935; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - HUGH THOMSON, HIS ART, HIS LETTERS, HIS HUMOR AND HIS CHARM
    - Research Notes
      - Notebooks
        - "Applications for Information", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 131)
        - "Hugh Thomson. Books. Authors - Publishers", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 132)
        - "Hugh Thomson in the Magazines", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 133)
        - "Illustrations and Plates" (Box 3, Folder 134)
        - "Letters from and to Hugh Thomson" (Box 3, Folder 135)
        - "Notices of Hugh Thomson in Books and Magazines and Newspapers" (Box 3, Folder 136)
        - Notebook with holograph notes on the typescript draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 137)
        - Pages from looseleaf research notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 138-140)
          Includes: Letter from Jessie Naismith (Miller) Thomson to MHS, 1922
      - Reminiscences about Hugh Thomson
        - Allen, Grace, typescript and holograph (Box 3, Folder 141)
          Includes: "Testimonials to Miss Grace Allen," printed item
        - Carey, Joseph W., holograph in the hand of John Vinycomb, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 142)
          Includes: Letter to MHS from John Vinycomb
        - Carr, Mrs. J. Comyns (Joseph Comyns), carbon typescript, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 143)
        - Chapman, Dinda[?], carbon typescript (Box 3, Folder 144)
          Includes: letter from Chapman to O. Pelly Dick
        - Dick, O. Pelly, typescript and carbon typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 145)
          Includes: Letter from A. G. Chuter to MHS, 1921
        - Hunter, Robert, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 146)
        - McNeill, John, holograph, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 147)
        - Thomson, Richard, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 148)
        - Vinycomb, John, holograph, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 149)
          Includes: Letter to MHS from JV, 1921
        - Unidentified, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 150)
      - Other Research Notes
        - "Bibliography of Hugh Thomson's Printed Work," holograph and carbon typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 151-152)
        - Chapter outline and list of sources used in each chapter, holograph (Box 3, Folder 153)
        - "List of drawings in the possession of A. & C. Black, Ltd. at July 6, 1931," carbon typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 154)
        - Lists of illustrations by HT used in the book, typescripts, carbon typescripts and holographs (Box 3, Folder 155-156)
        - Lists of exhibitions of HT's work, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 157)
        - Press notices on books illustrated by HT, holograph copies, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 158)
        - Reviews of books illustrated by HT, newspaper clippings and carbon typescripts, 1892-1931, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 159)
        - Other notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 160-161)
    - Drafts and Proofs
      - Introduction, notes and holograph draft (Box 4, Folder 162)
      - Holograph draft, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 163-177)
        Includes: Letter to MHS from "O. W."
      - Typescript, with holograph notes and corrections, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 178-186)
      - Carbon typescript, with holograph notes and corrections, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 187-192)
        Includes: Letter to MHS from W. H. Dodd
      - Chapter 2, fragment, galley proofs, corrected, [1931]
      - Galley proofs, corrected, [1931]
      - Chapter 1, fragment, page proofs, corrected, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 193)
      - Page 17 (actually pages 36-7), page proofs, 2 copies, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 194)
      - Page proofs, corrected, with book cover, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 195-198)
      - Proofs of several illustrations, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 199)
      - End paper illustration samples, [1931]
      - Cover originally containing proofs and typescript
    - Materials Collected After Publication
      - Book cover, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 200)
        With note concerning writings by Sir Isidore Spielmann
      - Book jackets, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 201)
      - Lists of papers to which copies of the book were sent, n.d.
      - Prospectuses, carbon typescript and printed versions, [1931] (Box 5, Folder 202)
      - Publication announcements, newspaper clippings, 1921-32, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 203)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings and holograph and typescript copies, 1931-33, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 204-205)
      - Other newspaper clippings mentioning the book, 1931-32 (Box 5, Folder 206)
      - Empty envelope with holograph listing press reviews, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - Amshewitz, M. H.
      - "A Tribute," holograph copy of a poem, 1935 May 23 (Box 5, Folder 208)
    - Spielmann, M. H.
      - "Hugh Thomson"
        [Full title: "Hugh Thomson," entry printed in the Dictionary of National Biography, supplement 1912-21, 1927]
        - "Notice to Contributors," printed version, 1921 Oct (Box 5, Folder 209)
        - Biographical chronology, holograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 210)
        - Holograph, corrected, [1925?] (Box 5, Folder 211)
        - Carbon typescript, corrected, [1925?] (Box 5, Folder 212)
    - Vinycomb, John
      - Article on HT for the catalog of an exhibition in Belfast, 17-19 May 1906, typescript (Box 5, Folder 213)
- Artwork, 1879-1923; Series III; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  - ARTWORK BY HUGH THOMSON
    - Illustrations for Books
      - As You Like It by William Shakespeare
        - Man and woman in the snow, pencil and watercolor (Box 6, Folder 214)
        - Man, woman and bird, pencil and watercolor
      - Evelina by Fanny Burney
        - "Much incommoded by three gentlemen," pen and ink, 1903
        - "They frequently looked back," pen and ink and watercolor, 1903
        - Woman and mirror, decoration for the list of illustrations, pen and ink, [1903]
      - Highways and Byways series
        - "Bristol from Brandon Hill," pencil (Box 6, Folder 215)
        - "At Chedworth," pencil, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 216)
        - "The Canal and Church at Frampton," pencil, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 217)
        - "The Cornish followed the lad up the hill," pen and ink, 1897
        - "The Market House, Newent," pencil, 1919 [Jul 10] (Box 6, Folder 218)
        - "A Welsh Drovers' race," photograph of a drawing, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 219)
        - "West Door, Lindisfarne Priory," pencil (Box 6, Folder 220)
        - Windmill, pencil (Box 6, Folder 221)
      - The History of Henry Esmond by William Makepeace Thackeray
        - "By the Great Crackling Fire," pen and ink and crayon[?], 1904
        - "Do I look very wicked, cousin?" pen and ink, 1905
        - "He kissed the fair hand," pen and ink and pencil, 1904
      - A Kentucky Cardinal, and Aftermath by James Lane Allen
        - "Certain Ladies who bow sweetly to me," pen and ink and pencil, 1900
        - Headpiece to chapter 6, pen and ink
        - "I Dressed up," pen and ink and pencil
        - "Little town boys into my strawberry bed," pen and ink and pencil, 1900
        - "Looking down at the gate that I made yesterday," pen and ink
        - Man at window, headpiece to chapter 11, pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 222)
        - "The New Neighbors have come," pen and ink and pencil, 1900
        - Sketches of decorative initials, pen and ink and pencil
        - "Welcomed her gayly," pen and ink and pencil, 1900
        - "When she fed her hens," pen and ink and pencil
      - Our Village by Mary Russell Mitford
        - "A Battle," pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 223)
        - "Blind Robert," pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 224)
        - "By Sheer Beggary," pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 225)
        - "The Copse," pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 226)
        - "Country Pictures," pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 227)
        - "Dipping up water," pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 228)
        - "Faster, faster!" pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 229)
        - "Hannah Bint," pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 230)
        - "And a horseman passing it at full trot," pen and ink, 1893 Jan (Box 6, Folder 231)
        - Illustration for the contents, two men with books, pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 232)
        - Illustration for the introduction, two women with a child, pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 233)
        - Illustration for the list of illustrations, man with four children, pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 234)
        - "In the old apple tree," pen and ink, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 235)
        - "A knowing look," pen and ink, 1893 Jan (Box 6, Folder 236)
        - "The little hussar," pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 237)
        - "The Little Postboy," pen and ink (Box 6, Folder 238)
        - "Little Rogues!" pen and ink